Register of the Vrangel' collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- NACHAL'NIK UPRAVLENIIA ZAGRANICHNAGO SNABZHENIIA, 1918-1923 (Boxes 55-73)
  Correspondence, contracts, purchase orders, and financial reports related to the purchase of military and other supplies for anti-Soviet forces in Siberia, North-West and South Russia. Includes correspondence of Lieut.-Gen. E. Hermonius with government agencies and private firms mostly in Great Britain, France and the U.S. Files 6-37, 39-44, 46-51, 60-80.
  - Office correspondence of Lieut.-Gen. E. Hermonius and other material related to the administration of his department, typescript and handwritten
    - (Group I, File 6)
      - Great Britain: Russkii Pravitel'svennyi Komitet v Londone, miscellaneous material including correspondence, reports and lists of military materiel ordered, January-March 1919 (Box 55, Folder 15-16)
        Available on microfilm reel 68
    - (Group I, File 7)
      - France: correspondence, reports and lists of materiel, mostly related to military purchases from French government and French military suppliers, 1921 (Folder 17-20)
    - (Group I, File 8)
      - Rumania: miscellaneous material, mostly related to recovery of Russian military property in Rumania, includes correspondence with French authorities and lists of supplies, May 1919-December 1920 (Box 56, Folder 1-4)
        Available on microfilm reel 69
    - (Group I, File 9) (Folder 5-9)
      - Great Britain: Londonskaia Likvidatsionnaia Komissiia re acquisiton of military supplies in Great Britain and their shipment to Crimea, October 1, 1920-August 1, 1921
    - (Group I, File 10)
      - Great Britain: Beliaev, Col., re purchase and shipment of aviation supplies from Great Britain for armies of Gen. A. Denikin, Also includes some correspondence re Italy and France, 1919 (Folder 10-13)
    - (Group I, File 11)
      - U.S.: correspondenc with Ambassador B. Bakhmetev and Finansovyi Agent S. Ughet re purchase and shipment of military supplies from U.S., January-October 1919 (Box 57, Folder 1-4)
        Available on microfilm reel 70
    - (Group I, File 12)
      - Upravlenie Rossiiskago Torgovago Flota and others re shipment of military supplies, January 1920-April 1921 (Folder 5-7)
    - (Group I, File 13)
      - Ministerstvo Putei Soobshcheniia and others re supply of railroads in territories newly liberated from the Bolsheviks, Includes reports and memoranda, December 1918-March 1920 (Folder 8-12)
        Folders 8-9 available on microfilm reel 70; folders 10-12 on reel 71
    - (Group I, File 14)
      - Russian, French and American officials and firms re supply of Armies of South Russia, Includes report, "Ocherk rabot Upravleniia Zagranichnago Snabzheniia Russkikh Armii za vremia IAnvar'-Iiul' 1919 goda", July-October 1919 (Folder 13-16)
        Available on microfilm reel 71
    - (Group I, File 15)
      - Miscellaneous material, including ledgers related to unloading of supply ships SS. "Sangamon" and "Balsam" in the Bay of Cattaro, March 1920-April 1921 (Box 58, Folder 1-4)
    - (Group I, File 16)
      - Supply of railroads on North-Western Front of Gen. N. IUdenich. Includes correspondence with Ministerstvo Putei Soobshcheniia, Russian Mission in Norway and "Obshchestvo sodeistviia razvitiiu zheleznykh dorog v Rossii,", August 1919-February 1920 (Folder 5-6)
        Available on microfilm reel 72
    - (Group I, File 17)
      - General correspondence, mostly with French military authorities and Upravlenie Rossiiskago Torgovago Flota re purchase and shipment of military supplies to South Russia; U.S., Ambassador B. Bakhmetev and Finansovyi Agent S. Ughet, mostly re supply of Petrograd by American Red Cross. Includes transcripts of telegrams from Omsk and Ekaterinodar, January 1919-January 1920 (Folder 7-11)
    - (Group I, File 18)
      - Same as above, January 1-July 1, 1919 (Box 59, Folder 1-5)
    - (Group I, File 19)
      - U.S.: Ambassador B. Bakhmetev and Finansovyi Agent S. Ughet re purchase of supplies, January 1-August 1, 1920 (Folder 6-9)
        Available on microfilm reel 73
    - (Group I, File 20)
      - Purchase and shipment of military supplies to armies in South Russia, mostly from France and the U.S. Includes transcripts of telegrams between Constantinople and Paris and "Doklad Zaveduiushchago Voennym Snabzheniem v Finansovo-Kontol'nuiu Komissiiu,", November 1-December 31, 1920 (Folder 10-13)
    - (Group I, File 21)
      - U.S.: A.R.A., Herbert Hoover, Col. J. Logan and R. Taft re supply of North Russian territories and Petrograd. Includes copy of "Special Agreement between the American Relief Administration and the Provisional Government of Russia," signed by Herbert Hoover and Lieut.-Gen. E. Hermonius and "Provisional Government of Russia Treasury Note of ," signed by Lieut.-Gen. E. Hermonius, N. de Basily and R. Taft, 1919 (Box 60, Folder 1-7)
        Folders 1-4 available on microfilm reel 73; folders 5-7 on reel 74
    - (Group I, File 22)
      - Administration of Gen. Kolchak re supply of Siberian government and army mostly from France, Great Britain and the U.S., 1919-1920 (Folder 8-11)
        Available on microfilm reel 74
    - (Group I, File 23)
      - Supply of Gen. N. IUdenich and the Armies of the North-West, mostly with French military authorities and Mission Militaire Britannique près le Gouvernement Français, March 1919-February 1920 (Folder 12-16)
        Folders 12-13 available on microfilm reel 74; folders 14-16 on reel 75
    - (Group I, File 24)
      - General correspondence re military supplies with private firms and individuals, mostly French and British, January 1920-June 1921 (Box 61, Folder 1-5)
        Available on microfilm reel 75
    - (Group I, File 25)
      - France: supply of Armies of South Russia, business records and correspondence, mostly with private firms and French military authorities, November 1-December 31 1919 (Folder 6-10)
        Available on microfilm reel 76
    - (Group I, File 26)
      - Germany: including Russian and Allied representatives in Germany and German officials re military supplies and especially war materiel captured by Germany during the war, 1920 (Folder 11-15)
    - (Group I, File 27)
      - Purchase of medical supplies for Armies of the North-West (Arkhangel'sk and Murmansk), mostly with French military authorities. Also purchase of telegraph for Flotilla of Arctic Ocean, October 1918-December 1919 (Box 62, Folder 1-4)
        Available on microfilm reel 77
    - (Group I, File 28)
      - Great Britain: Londonskaia Zagotovitel'naiai Komissiia, British War Office, Ministry of Munitions and private firms re supply for Russian Armies and civilian population in territories liberated from Bolsheviks, August-December 1919 (Folder 5-8)
    - (Group I, File 29)
      - General. Especially re relationship of French, English and German political circles to White cause, including reports of Prof. D. Gardner re political situation in Great Britain. Also includes commercial contract of Union of Siberian Dairy Cooperatives for purchase of supplies in the U.S. for White Army, 1920 (Folder 9-12)
    - (Group I, File 30)
      - Italy: including Missione Militare Russa, Direzione per gli Approvigionamenti Russi in Italia, re purchase and transportation of binoculars and aviation supplies, January 1919-December 1920 (Folder 13-17)
        Folders 13-14 available on microfilm reel 77; folders 15-17 on reel 78
    - (Group I, File 31)
      - France: reports re condition of materiel shipped to Russian forces; contracts between Gen. E. Hermonius and "Ateliers d'aviation Louis Breguet" and "Spad" for purchase of airplanes; miscellaneous orders for clothing, France and England; order for telephone cable, Belgium; orders for motorcycles and sidecars, France, October 1, 1920-December 1921 (Box 63, Folder 1-4)
        Available on microfilm reel 78
      - (Group I, File 32) (Folder 5-8)
      - Lists of supplies stored in Vladivostok; transportation to Omsk of aeronautical and artillery supplies purchased in France, January 1918-February 1920
      - (Group I, File 33)
      - Germany: purchase of military supplies for armies of Gen. N. IUdenich and Gen. A. Denikin; transfer of military supplies siezed by the Germans during the war, includes memoranda to Allied governments from Gen. D. SHcherbachev, Russian Military Representative with the Allied High Command and Commandement en Chef des Armées Alliées (Gens. Foch and Weygand); administrative and financial matters: Col. Brant, Nachal'nik Russkoi Delegatsii po delam voenoplennykh i bezhentsev v Germanii, September 1919-January 1920 (Folder 9-12)
        Folder 9 available on microfilm reel 78; folders 10-12 on reel 79
    - (Group I, File 34)
      - General, re purchase and transport of military supplies from France, Great Britain, U.S., Czechoslovakia and Japan, includes inventory lists of military supplies stored in France, Rumania and the U.S., also lists of material ordered; Bulgaria: transfer of military supplies from Bulgarian government to V.S.IU.R., January 1-July 31, 1920 (Box 64, Folder 1-6)
        Available on microfilm reel 79
    - (Group I, File 35)
      - Same as above, March 1-December 10, 1919 (Folder 7-10)
        Available on microfilm reel 80
    - (Group I, File 36)
      - Orders, typescript
        - Miller, Lieut.-Gen. E.
          - Glavnoupolnomochennyi po Voennym i Morskim Delam Glavnokomanduiushchago V.S.IU.R, No. 1-8, July 27-October 21, 1920 (Folder 11)
          - Voennyi Predstavitel' Glavnokomanduiushchago Russkoi Armiei pri Pravitel'stve Frantsuzskoi Respubliki, No. 9-16, and No. 1, January 20, 1921, November 5-December 31, 1920 (Folder 12)
          - Hermonius, Lieut.-Gen. E., Upravlenie Voennago Snabzheniia, No. 1-40, August 19, 1920-February 24, 1921 (Folder 13)
      - Administration: reports and correspondence, mostly re departmental finance and personnel; closing of department and liquidation of its assets, typescript and handwritten, February 1920-July 1921 (Folder 14-15)
    - (Group I, File 37)
      - Orders, typescript
        - Hermonius, Lieut.-Gen. E., Upravlenie Zagranichnago Snabzheniia Russkikh Armii, No. 1-7, January 25, 1919-February 27, 1920 (Folder 16)
        - SHcherbachev, Gen. D.
          - Voennyi Predstavitel' Verkhovnago Pravitelia Za-granitsei, No. 1-3, July 27-August 31, 1919 (Folder 17)
          - Voennyi Predstavitel' Verkhovnago Pravitelia pri Soiuznykh Pravitel'stvakh i Komandovanii, No. 3-, August 31, 1919 (Folder 18)
      - Administration: reports and correspondence, mostly re departmental finance and personnel; correspondence with French authorities re repatriation of Russian officers, typescript and handwritten, April 1919-January 1920 (Folder 19-20)
    - (Group I, File 38) See below, UPRAVLENIE PREDSTAVITELIA GLAVNOKOMANDUIUSHCHAGO SEVERO-ZAPADNOI ARMIEI
    - (Group I, File 39)
    - Inventory of supplies sent to Armies of the North-West (Gen. N. IUdenich), Arkhangel'sk, Vladivostok, South Russia (Gen. A. Denikin) and Government of Kuban; correspondence and reports, Ministère de la Guerre and Direction du Contrôle Service Interministériel des Dépenses à l'Etranger and Upravlenie Rossiiskim Torgovym Flotom, typescript and handwritten, January 1919-July 1920 (Box 65, Folder 1-4)
      Available on microfilm reel 81
    - (Group I, File 40)
      - Purchase of military supplies, mostly aeronautical. Includes transcripts of telegrams between Paris, London, Constantinople and Sevastopl', 1920-1921 (Folder 5-6)
    - (Group I, File 41)
      - France: purchase of military supplies, mostly aeronautical, Paris, June-February 1919 (Folder 7-8)
    - (Group I, File 42)
      - Great Britain: correspndence with Voennoe Vedomstvo po Zakazam v Velikobritanii (Col. Beliaev), Londonskaia Likvidatsionnaia Komissiia and embassies in London and Washington; inventories and reports re supplies purchased, their transportation and liquidation; protocol, Komissiia Upolnomochennykh Vedomstv, January 1-June 1, 1920 (Folder 9-13)
    - (Group I, File 43)
      - Great Britain: lists of supplies to be ordered, including telephone, telegraph and radio equipment, mostly for Army Communication and Geographical Services, February-November 1919 (Box 66, Folder 1-2)
        Available on microfilm reel 82
    - (Group I, File 44)
      - U.S.: reports re work of Otdel po Snabzheniiu pri Rossiiskom Posol'stve v Vashingtone; correspondence of Ambassador B. Bakhmetev and Finansovyi Agent S. Ughet, inludes material re Herbert Hoover; correspondence of Gen. E. Hermonius with U.S. War Department Director of Sales, Paris, October 1-December 31, 1919 (Folder 3-6)
    - (Group I, File 45) See below, UPRAVLENIE PREDSTAVITELIA GLAVNOKOMANDUIUSHCHAGO SEVERO-ZAPADNOI ARMIEI
    - (Group I, File 46)
      - Great Britain: correspondence of Col. Beliaev, Russian Government Committee in London and Voennoe Vedomstvo po Zakazam v Anglii; miscellaneous material, including protocols of meetings of Likvidatsionnii Komitet v Londone (Nos. 1-12) and Soveshchanie Upolnomochennykh Vedomstv; Russian Union of Zemstvos and Towns re purchase of medical supplies; inventories of military supplies ordered and their liquidation; miscellaneous material re radio equipment, April-July 1919 (Folder 7-13)
    - (Group I, File 47)
      - France: purchase of military supplies; correspondence with Ministère de la Guerre and individual firms; inventories of supplies ceded by French government; report, "Svedenie Upravleniia Zaveduiushchago Voennym Snabzheniem o summakh uplachennykh frantsuzskomu Pravitel'stvu za ustuplennyie armii Gen. Vrangelia predmety voennago snabzheniia,"; correspondence files re individual orders, 1920-1921, March 1921 (Folder 14-16)
        Folder 14 available on microfilm reel 82; folders 15-16 on reel 83
    - (Group I, File 48)
      - France: purchase of military supplies for Gen. Vrangel's army; correspondence with G.H.Q., Nachal'nik Snabzhenii Russkoi Armii, Ministerstvo Innostrannykh Del (P. Struve and V. Maklakov) and various administrative departments of V.S.IU.R.; Russian Ambassador in Constantinople, French Ministère de la Guerre and Comité Militaire Allié de Versailles, Section Française; lists of supplies required by Russian Army, August 1-October 30, 1920 (Box 67, Folder 1-5)
        Available on microfilm reel 83
    - (Group I, File 49)
      - Great Britain: supply of V.S.IU.R. in Crimea, including Likvidatsionnaia Kommissiia v Londone (with list of officials serving on commission), Voennoe Vedomstvo po Zakazam v Anglii (Col. Beliaev); minutes of meetings, Komitet po Delam Snabzheniia i Finansov,; lists of supplies required by Russian Army; lists of supplies sent to Crimea, June 1-October 1, 1920, July 16-September 28 (Box 67, Folder 6-9)
    - (Group I, File 50)
      - France and Great Britain: miscellaneous material re ss. "Siam" bound from Brest for Sevastopol', includes invoices and manifests, September 1920-June, 1921 (Box 67, Folder 10-13)
        Available on microfilm reel 84
    - (Group I, File 51)
      - Northern Army, Arkhangel'sk and Finnish Sector under Gen. E. Miller: lists of supplies required; correspondence with Londonskaia Komissiia po Zagranichnomu Snabzheniiu; correspondence, Gen. E. Miller and N. CHaikovskii, including transcripts of telegrams from Gen. E. Miller; miscellaneous material re supplies stored at Bergen, Sweden; correspondence, Ministère de la Guerre; transfer of supplies, American Red Cross and government of Rumania, March 1919-March 1920 (Box 68, Folder 1-5)
    - (Group I, File 52, 53 and 55-59) See below, ROSSIISKII VOENNYI AGENT V KONSTANTINOPOLE
    - (Group I, File 60)
      - U.S.: "Spravka o Dvizhenii Imushchestva Otdela po Snabsheniiu,"; protocols, "Soveshchanie po Voprosu o Prodovol'stvovanii Petrograda," New York, October 6-November 25, 1919; administrative matters, complaint of Artillery, May 1, 1918-June 15, 1919 (Box 68, Folder 6-8)
      - Artificer-Officer Stepanov, May 1918-February 1920
    - (Group I, File 61)
      - France: military supplies purchased from the French government
        - Packing lists (bordereau de sortie) for aeronautical supplies destined for Mission Française en Sibérie (Folder 7)
        - Invoices, miscellaneous military materiel destined for Army of the North-West, Gen. N. IUdenich, typescript forms, December 1919-April 1920 (Folder 8)
        - Receipts, bills and correspondence concerning payment, includes supplies destined for Gen. P. Vrangel', typescript and handwritten, November 1919-March 1921 (Folder 9)
          Available on microfilm reel 85
    - (Group I, File 62)
      - Correspondence between Nachal'nik Upravleniia Zagranichnago Snabzheniia, Gen. E. Hermonius and Upolnomochennyi Gosudarstvennago Kontrolia, August-November 1920 (Box 68, Folder 10-14)
    - (Group I, File 63)
      - f supplies to Russian Armies of North-West and South, includes correspondence with Ministère de la Guerre; reports, "Vedomost' Otpravok v Rossiiu Voennago Imushchestva iz Russkikh Skladov vo Frantsii...," November 1919... "Vedomost' Voennago Immushchestva, Predlagaemago k Otpravke v Blizhaishee Vremia," November 1919, "Vedomost' Likvidirovannago vo Frantsii Artilleriiskago Imushchestva," December 1919; protocols nos. 1-3 of "Zasedanie Komissii o likvidatsii imushchestva priobretennago dlia nuzhd Krymskoi Armii...," November 1920; lists of supplies shipped from the U.S. to Sebastopol; lists of supplies in possession of Zavedyvaiushchii Voennym Snabzheniem, January 1921; March 1919-March 1921 (Box 69, Folder 1-3)
    - (Group I, File 64)
      - France: acquisition of artillery supplies, including correspondence with Schneider & Cie. Commission des Poudres de Guerre de Versailles, Ministère de la Guerre, Direction de l'Artillerie; purchase of Wetterli cartridges and ordnance supplies (includes reports of Ministère de la Guerre, 1915), August 1919-February 1920, (August-September 1919) (Box 69, Folder 4-8)
        Available on microfilm reel 86
    - (Group I, File 65)
      - France: correspondence with American Red Cross in Paris (Major C. Payson) and French authorities re medical supplies to be shipped to Vladivostok, Novorossiisk and North-West Russia; list of Petrograd children in charge of American Red Cross, enroute from Vladivostok to Western Europe; April 1919-April 1920, (July 1920) (Box 69, Folder 9-12)
    - (Group I, File 66)
      - Formation of anti-Bolshevik military movement, typescript and handwritten material, May 1918-August 1919
        - Organization, political and military goals of White Army, mostly information for Allied Governments
          - General (Box 70, Folder 1)
          - North Russia, including North-Western Army of Gen. N. IUdenich, the Baltic Provinces and Finland (Folder 2)
          - Western Volunteer Army (Folder 3)
        - Supply: lists of military supplies required by White Armies; information re supplies available abroad, including "Inventaire 1. Des stocks appartenant au gouvernement russe ou aux particuliers russes 2. Des contrats dont la livraison auxdites personnes n'est pas terminée," Paris Imprimerie Nationale, 1918 (Folder 4-6)
        - Press: communiques of emigre press, includes Union and La Cause commune of V. Burtsev, typescript, May-July 1919; pro-Soviet letter from Moscow of Jean Longuet, dir. Populaire, January 1919 (Folder 7)
    - (Group I, File 67)
      - France: correspondence with Société Russe et Française pour le Commerce, l'Industrie et les Transports, typescript, July-December 1920 (Box 70, Folder 8-10)
        Available on microfilm reel 87
    - (Group I, File 68)
      - France and Great Britain: purchase of medical supplies, mostly for Government of Kuban', includes correspondence with Gouvernement du Kouban, Ministère de la Santé; American Red Cross; Deloproizvoditel' Sanitarnoi CHasti (Dr. V. Fedorovskii); Parizhskaia Komissiia po Snabzheniiu Russkikh Armii, Sanitarnyi Otdel; Ministère de la Guerre; Komitet Soiuza Zemstva i Gorodov v Londone; Osoboe Soveshchanie po Delam Rossiiskago Obshchestva Krasnago Kresta za Granitsei; French pharmaceutical companies, April-December 1919 (Box 70, Folder 11-14)
    - (Group I, File 69)
      - U.S.: purchase of military supplies, includes correspondence with Ambassador B. Bakhmetev and Finansovyi Agent S. Ughet; transcripts of telegrams between New York, Paris, London, Constantinople and Tokyo; lists of supplies; purchasing contracts; report re shipment of goods from Japan to Crimea, August 1920-August 1921 (Folder 15-17)
        Folder 15 available on microfilm reel 87; folders 16-17 on reel 88
    - (Group I, File 70)
      - France: contracts and receipts for miscellaneous supplies; correspondence with Inspektor Priemok; "Instruktsiia priemshchikam"; correspondence and instructions of Ministère de la Guerre, Sous-Secrétaire d'Etat du Service de Santé Militaire, March 1919-November 1920 (Box 71, Folder 1-2)
        Available on microfilm reel 88
    - (Group I, File 71)
      - Miscellaneous material re supply of Russian Armies by France, Great Britain and the U.S., includes correspondence with Ministère de la Guerre and other French departments; drafts of contracts with French government for export of Russian grain and raw materials as payment for military supplies; transcripts of telegrams from Taganrog, Omsk and Constantinople; report re supply of Gen. N. IUdenich and Petrograd; supplies stored at Bergen; judicial enquiries re mismanagement in supply (London: Kaminskii and Voevodskii, Paris: Sviderskii); lists of supplies required by Russian Armies, August 1919-November 1921 (Folder 3-7)
    - (Group I, File 72)
      - France: miscellaneous material re purchase of artillery and other supplies for army of Gen. A. Denikin and N. IUdenich, includes correspondence with Ministère de la Guerre, invoices and packing lists, July 1919-March 1920 (Folder 8-10)
    - (Group I, File 73)
      - France and Great Britain: shipment of supplies, including medical supplies of American Red Cross and French military materiel, principally aboard ss. "Olga"; correspondence and official complaints of Russian authorities to British Admiralty re mismanagement in loading cargo of cartridges aboard ss. "Olga,", December 1919-November 1920 (Folder 11-14)
        Available on microfilm reel 89
    - (Group I, File 74)
      - Supply of Gen. N. IUdenich and Armies of the North-West (including Finliandsko-Estliandskaia Gruppa): correspondence and transcripts of telegrams to and from Gen. N. Iudenich, Russian government agencies (Omsk, Paris, London, Stockholm, Copenhagen, Washington, Brussels), Ministère de la Guerre, American Red Cross, Canadian Red Cross; lists of supplies (including artillery, aeronautical, railroad and sanitary), required and sent, January-November 1919 (Box 72, Folder 1-7)
    - (Group I, File 75)
      - Reports of Gen. E. Hermonius to Representative of State Comptroller's Office (Upolnomochennyi Gosudarstvennago Kontrolia na Zapade), includes "Otchet Zavedyvaiushchago Voennym Snabzheniem v izraskhodovanii kredita poluchennago na...Programma Zakazov No. 1-C,"; "Opis'...opravdatel'nykh dokumentov, prilozhennykh k otchetam Zavedyvaiushchago Voennym Snabzheniem v izraskhodovanii kreditov, poluchennykh na ispolnenie zakazov..."; "Vedomost' ispolneniia zakazov...programmy No. 1-13C," July-October 1920... "Raschet s Frantsuzskim Voennym Ministerstvom po postavkam Armii Generala Vrangelia ppredmetov voennago snabzheniia za vremia s I-go avgusta 1920 g. po I-e fevralia 1921 g. cherez Otdel Voennago Snabzheniia"; "Obshchee svedenie o sostoianii kreditov Otdela Zavedyvaiushchago Voennym Snabzheniem," April 1, February 1, 1921, February 1921 (Folder 8-13)
        Folders 8-10 available on microfilm reel 89; folders 11-13 on reel 90
    - (Group I, File 76)